MIRCEA ZLOTEANU

Research Associate, PhD

mircea@eyethink.org \$\mathbb{L}_{+44} (0) 778 664 8601 \$\mathbb{Q}_{\text{London, UK, WC1E 6BT}}\$

RESEARCH PROFILE

I am an experimental psychology researcher interested in nonverbal communication, emotions, and deception detection. My research focuses on the behavioural cues used to ascertain if people are being truthful or deceptive. My work involves the effect of adopting specific postures when interacting with others, differences in judgements and perceptions made alone or in groups, the role of situational factors on accuracy and bias, the production of deceptive facial expressions, and on improving interrogation practices. Recently, my research focuses on the role of trust and reputation in the use of sharing economies and online platforms.

ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

2017 – Present **Research Associate**

University College London Computer Science Department

Project Title: The Role of Trust and Reputation in Sharing Economies

Supervisor: Giacomo Livan

I am the primary behavioural researcher investigating how trust and reputation influence user interaction and decision-making in sharing economies.

EDUCATION

2012 - 2017 PhD in Experimental Psychology

University College London

Thesis: Emotions and Deception Detection.

Supervisor: Daniel C. Richardson

My PhD focused on uncovering the importance of emotions in deception detection, attempting to understand their usefulness and their limitations as diagnostic cues.

2011 - 2012 **MSc in Social Cognition (Distinction)**

University College London

Dissertation: The Effect of Body Posture on Facial Expression Recognition and Deception

Detection.

Supervisor: Daniel C. Richardson

2007 - 2010 BSc (Hons) in Psychology (First Class, 1:1)

Goldsmiths College, University of London

2002 - 2007 International School of Bucharest (ISB)

First in Graduating Class

4 A Levels, 2 AS Levels, 6 IGCSEs

RESEARCH & PUBLICATIONS

Zloteanu, M. (2016 – in progress). Social Acuity: The Effect of Body Postures on Eye-gaze and Detecting Deception.

- **Zloteanu, M.** (2015). The role of emotions in detecting deception. In E. Williams & I. Sheeha, *Deception: An Interdisciplinary Exploration* (pp. 203-217). Oxford: Inter-Disciplinary Press.
- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (in prep.). The role of handcuffs in perception of guilt and the ability to detect deception.
- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (in prep.). Surprise! I'm not actually surprised the ability to fake an emotion.
- **Zloteanu**, M. (in progress). Deception Detection and Emotion Recognition: A Dual-Systems Approach.
- Patterson, A. & **Zloteanu**, **M.** (in progress). Perceived Lie Detection Ability: Wizards and Laypersons in Negotiations.
- **Zloteanu**, M. (submitted). Emotion recognition ability and Deception Detection in Low-stakes lying.
- **Zloteanu**, M. & Richardson, D.C. (submitted). Investigating the role of emotion in deception detection.
- Zloteanu, M. & Richardson, D.C. (submitted). Deception Detection in individuals and pairs.

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (2017). Passive Lie Detection. *Talk presented at SARMAC XII, Sydney, Australia.*
- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (2015). The Effect of Handcuffs on Deception Detection Visual and Audio Differences. *Poster presented at DECEPTICON I Cambridge, UK*.
- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (2015). Looking Ready for Jail The Influence of Handcuffs on Deception Detection and Suspiciousness. *Talk presented at SARMAC XI Victoria, BC, Canada*.
- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (2015). "Surprise! I'm not actually surprised" the ability to fake an emotion. *Talk presented at ISRE 2015, University of Geneva, Switzerland.*
- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (2015). Looking Ready for Jail The Influence of Handcuffs on Deception Detection and Suspiciousness. *Poster presented at the Faculty of Brain Sciences Annual Post-Graduate Research Poster and Presentation Symposium, London, University College London.*
- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (2015). "Surprise! I'm not actually surprised" the ability to fake an emotion. *Poster presented at the Society of Personality and Social Psychology, Long Beach, California*.
- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (2014). Emotion Recognition Training and Deception Detection: Importance of the type of lie told. *Poster presented at the Faculty of Brain Sciences Annual Post-Graduate Research Poster and Presentation Symposium, London, University College London.*
- **Zloteanu, M.** (2014). Deception Detection in low-stakes lies. *Talk presented at the Cumberland Lodge Conference, West Berkshire, UK*.
- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (2014). Investigating the role of emotion in deception detection. *Poster presented at the International Association for Conflict Management, Leiden, Netherlands.*
- **Zloteanu, M.** (2014). The role of emotions in detecting low-stakes lies. *Talk presented at the 1st Global Inter-disciplinary Deception Conference, Oxford, UK.*
- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (2013). Difference in Single vs. Pair judgements on Deception Detection, Confidence and Bias based on the Level of Communication. *Poster to be presented at the Thirty-Fifth Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society, Berlin, Germany, Cognitive*

Science Society.

- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (2013). Difference in Single vs. Pair judgements on Deception Detection, Confidence and Bias based on the Level of Communication. *Poster to be presented at the Joint Action Meeting 5, Berlin, Germany, Humboldt University*.
- **Zloteanu, M.** & Richardson, D.C. (2013). The effect of Body Posture and Empathy on the Recognition of Facial Expressions of Emotions and Deception Detection. *Poster to be presented at the Embodied & Situated Language Processing Conference, Potsdam, Germany.*
- **Zloteanu, M.** (2013). The effect of Body Posture and Empathy on the Recognition of Facial Expressions of Emotions and Deception Detection. *Poster presented at the Cumberland Lodge Conference, West Berkshire, UK*.

HONOURS & AWARDS

- 2017 PsyPAG Workshop Grant £1,139
- 2017 SARMAC Student Travel Award \$500
- 2015 SPSP Diversity Travel Award \$250
- 2015 UCL Graduate School Student Conference Award £600
- 2014 FBS Poster Symposium Best Poster (Runner up) £200
- 2014 Cumberland Lodge Bursary £100
- 2013 UCL Graduate School Student Conference Award £404
- 2012 Impact award, UCL Graduate School £32,500

TEACHING AND MENTORING

Lecturer and Invited Talks

- 2016 Lecture on "Detecting Deception Physiological, Verbal, and Nonverbal Techniques" Cognitive Psychology Course for the MSc in Research Methods University College London
- 2015 Lecture on "Emotions in Deception Detection"

 Cognitive Psychology Course for the MSc in Research Methods

 University College London
- 2014 Guest speaker on "Applied Social Psychology"

 Understanding Individuals and Groups module for the MSc in Social Cognition
 University College London

Lecture on "Methods of Detecting Deception – Physiological, Verbal, and Nonverbal" Introduction to Social Psychology Course for the BSc in Psychology New York University

Demonstrator

2014 – Present

BSc Psychology 2nd year Students – Research and Quantitative Methods in Psychology Module (40 students) University College London

2013 – Present

BSc Psychology 1st year Students — Introduction to Psychological Experimentation Module (10 students) University College London

Mentor

- 2016 BSc Psychology 3rd year Thesis projects (1 student) University College London
- 2015 BSc Psychology 3rd year Thesis projects (3 students)

 Undergraduate Summer Research assistants (4 students)

 University College London
- 2014 BSc Psychology 3rd year Final project (3 students)

 MSc Social Cognition Thesis project (1 student)

 University College London
- 2013 BSc Psychology 2nd year Mini-research projects (2 students) University College London

BSc Psychology 3rd year Affiliate Research project (1 student) University College London/ University of Pennsylvania

Group Coordinator

2013 - 2014 Post-Graduate Peer Group (PPG) president University College London

Invigilator

2013 2 x Statistics examination for MSc, MRes, and PhD students University College London (Autumn)

Statistics examination for MSc, MRes, and PhD students University College London (Winter)

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

Educational or Professional Qualifications:

Associate Fellow – Higher Education Academy (HEA) (2015) Certified – Developing Your Teaching: Centre for Advancing Learning and Teaching (CALT) (2014)

Professional Associations and Society Memberships:

- 2015 Deception International Conference on Deceptive Behavior
- 2015 ISRE International Society for Research on Emotion
- 2015 SARMAC The Society for Applied Research in Memory and Cognition
- 2014 IACM The International Association for Conflict Management
- 2014 Inter-disciplinary.net Deception 1st Global Deception Conference
- 2014 SPSP The Society for Personality and Social Psychology
- 2013 PsyPAG Psychology Postgraduate Affairs Group
- 2013 CogSci Cognitive Science Society
- 2013 ESLP Embodied and Situated Language Processes
- 2013 JAM Joint Action Meeting

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

Reviewer

Submissions reviewer, Decepticon 2015: *International Conference on Deceptive Behavior*, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK 24-26 August 2015

Assistant reviewer, Journal of Nonverbal Behavior, April 2015

PROFESSIONAL TRAINING

Doctoral training courses completed:

Negotiation Skills Matlab for Cognitive Neuroscience Scientific Programming in Python

R Studio Advanced Statistics

Skills for Conflict Resolution

RED250 Mobile Eyetracker Workshop

Teaching training courses completed:

Teaching in Higher Education Context and Problem Based Learning Students' Mental Health Support Using Audience Response Systems for Teaching

WORK EXPERIENCE

2014 – Present **Private tutor in Statistics, SPSS, and Psychology**

The Profs Tuition Ltd

2010 – 2011 Media Administrative Assistant

Westgate Labels Srl

2008 – 2009 Office Assistant to Chief Dental Surgeon/Director

Tomdent Srl

FURTHER QUALIFICATIONS

IELTS Examination (2008) Academic Module: Grade 8 BEC (Business English Certificate) Vantage: Grade A Romanian Computer Programming Olympiad (2006)

SKILLS & TRAINING

Languages

Romanian (mother tongue)

English (fluent)

French (intermediate level)

Spanish (intermediate level)

Japanese (basic level)

German (basic level)

Computer skills

Qualtrics, Amazon Mturk, e-Prime, Android SDK, Advanced knowledge of Microsoft ® Windows environments, iOS environment, Linux environment, Microsoft Office package, Photoshop CC, InDesign, GIMP, Outlook, Thunderbird, basic programming (C++, Python, MatLab), Website design (CSS, Java, JavaScript, HTML), Content Management systems (Drupal, etc.), cPanel.

Statistical Programs

SPSS, MatLab, R studio, Stata, G-Power, BayesFactor, SMI BeGaze.

REFERENCES

Dr. Daniel C. Richardson (primary supervisor) Department of Experimental Psychology University College London dcr@eyethink.org

Dr. Eva Krumhuber Department of Experimental Psychology University College London e.krumhuber@ucl.ac.uk

Dr. Ruud Custers
Department of Experimental Psychology
University College London
r.custers@ucl.ac.uk